A Guide to the Nelson Family Papers, 1783-1872, n.d.
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Nelson Family Papers, 1783-1872, n.d.
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Nelson family; Nelson, Adelaide, 1816-1875; Nelson, George Washington, Jr., 1840-1903; Nelson, Hugh Mortimer, Sr., 1811-1862
Ms1989-021
0.9 Cubic Feet 3 boxes
This collection contains papers (primarily correspondence and Civil War documents) from the Nelson family of Clarke County, Virginia, 1783-1872, n.d.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by Special Collections in 1989.
Biographical note
The Nelson family has a long and rich history in the state of Virginia beginning with Thomas Nelson (1677–1745) who came to Yorktown in the early years of the 18th century and is often identified as Scotch Tom. Among his sons was William Nelson (1711–72), colonial governor of Virginia (1771–71), sometimes known as "President Nelson," as he held the title, President and Commander in Chief of the Colony and Dominion of Virginia; and Thomas Nelson (1716–82), known as Secretary Nelson, who served as secretary of the Virginia Colony. One of William's son's, Thomas Nelson (1738–89) represented Virginia in the Continental Congress, was a signer of the Declaration of Independence, and was Governor of Virginia in 1781. Governor Thomas Nelson and his wife, Lucy Grymes had eleven children, all of whom were born at Yorktown. Among Governor Thomas Nelson and Lucy Grymes's children were Thomas Nelson Jr. (b. 1764), Philip Nelson (b. 1766), and Francis Nelson (b. 1767).
Thomas Nelson Jr. married Frances Page in 1795 and had four children, including Rev. George Washington Nelson (b. 1805), who married Jane Crease in 1834. They had three children, including George Washington Nelson, Jr. (b. 1840), also known as "Wash." He attended University of Virginia from 1858 to 1860, but, in May 1861, enlisted in the Confederate Army. Within a year, he was a Captain commanding the Hanover Light Artillery, soon to be promoted to Major. In October 1862, outside New Market in Millwood, Clarke County, Va., he was captured by Union forces and spent the rest of the war as a prisoner. Confined first at Atheneum Prison, West Virginia, he was transferred to Camp Chase, Ohio; Johnson's Island, Ohio; Pt. Lookout then Hammond General Hospital, Maryland; and then to Ft. Delaware, Delaware in June 1864. On 20 August 1864, he was moved to Morris Island outside Charleston, South Carolina, where he become one of what is known as the Immortal 600, a group of confederate prisoners placed by the Union in the line of Confederate fire, in retaliation for a similar action by the Confederate Army. "Wash" was moved again to Ft. Pulaski, Georgia, where he was finally released in June 1865. His correspondence with cousin Mollie Scollay, written while he was a prisoner of war, is a prominent part of this collection. He and Mollie were married in October 1865. George Washington Nelson, Jr. was ordained as a Episcopal priest in 1875 and had been rector of St. James Episcopal Church in Warrenton, Va. for over twenty years at the time of his death on 30 May 1903. Mollie died on 12 June 1923.
Philip Nelson married Sarah Ann Burwell in 1789 and moved to Clarke Co. Va. together with Sarah's brother, Robert Carter Burwell in 1790. Robert Carter Burwell was the builder of the home "Rosney" and, about twenty years later, the nearby mansion at Long Branch Plantation, both of Clarke County. Burwell died while serving in the military during the War of 1812, after which Philip and Sarah Nelson, who had lived at Rosney, inherited Long Branch.
Francis Nelson of Mont Air, Hanover Co. Va. married Lucy Page about 1792 and had fourteen children. Among them were Sally Page Nelson (b. 1801), Hugh Mortimer Nelson (b. 1811), and Fannie Burwell Nelson (b. 1810).
Sally Page Nelson married Dr. Samuel Scollay of Smithfield, Jefferson County, Va. (later West Virginia) in 1841. Among their children was Mary Scollay (b. 1844), also known as Mollie. It is Mollie's correspondence with George Washington ("Wash") Nelson, Jr., her future husband, while he was a prisoner of war that forms a large part of this collection. "Wash" and Mollie were cousins, as their fathers, Thomas Nelson, Jr. and Francis Nelson, were brothers. They were both grandchildren of Governor Thomas Nelson.
Hugh Mortimer Nelson (Sr.) married Adelaide Holker (b. 1816) of Boston in 1836. They settled in Baltimore for a short time, where Hugh began his career as a lawyer. In 1842, Hugh moved back to Virginia with his wife and three-year old daughter Nannie and purchased a struggling Long Branch from his uncle Philip Nelson. The correspondence between Adelaide and daughter Nannie while the latter was attending a New York school in 1857 comprises another significant portion of this collection. Son Hugh Nelson, Jr. was born in 1847. Another daughter, Lucy, was born in 1842, but died as an infant. Hugh Mortimer Nelson, Sr. represented Clarke County at the Virginia (Secession) Convention of 1861, where he initially maintained his support for the Union. Following the events at Ft. Sumter and Virginia's decision to secede, he raised a cavalry company from Clarke County and served under J.E.B. Stuart's command for a time before attaining the rank of Major under General Richard S. Ewell. Wounded at the Battle of Gaines Mill/Seven Days Battles on 26 June 1862, he died in Albemarle County on 6 August 1862. Adelaide was left in charge of Long Branch. She died in 1875 of pneumonia after a long struggle to keep the property in the family.
Fanny Burwell Nelson, one of Hugh Mortimer Nelson, Sr's sisters, never married and moved from Mont Air, Hanover County to Smithfield, Jefferson County, Va. (later West Virginia) around 1846. She moved from Smithfield to Long Branch in 1878 when it belonged to Hugh Mortimer Nelson, Jr. and his wife, Sally Page Nelson (b. 1866), daughter of George Washington ("Wash") Nelson, Jr. and Mary (Mollie) Scollay Nelson. Fanny Burwell Nelson died at Long Branch in 1896.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of papers, primarily correspondence, from the Nelson family of Clarke County, Virginia. The Civil War letters between prisoner of war George Washington "Wash" Nelson and his future wife, Mollie Scollay of Shepardstown, Jefferson County, Virginia (now West Virginia) make up the largest part of the collection, followed by the correspondence between Hugh and Adelaide Nelson of Long Branch Plantation and their daughter Nannie. Other Civil War papers include muster rolls, one of them signed by J.E.B. Stuart, of Captain Hugh Mortimer Nelson Sr.'s companies in the First and the Sixth Virginia Cavalry
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series, Correspondence and Documents. Items within the first series are arranged, first, by primary correspondent, and then by date, when possible. Items withing the second series are arranged by the family member with whom the document is associated.
Box 1 Folders 24 and 25 were removed in June 2014 and refoldered as Oversize Folder 1.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Women -- History
Geographical Names:
Clarke County (Va.)
Contents List
- June 17, 1828 Prescription for Nelson Esq. from a Pharmacy in Parish (Box 1, Folder 1)
- July 1, 1836, From P. Graften, Jr. in New York City to Hugh M. Nelson, Esq. Re. a horse (Box 1, Folder 2)
- February 16, 1838, Letter from J.H. Mason in Washington, D.C. to Hugh M. Nelson, Esq. in Baltimore, Maryland, Re. The whereabouts of a clerk (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1857, Letter from Adelaide in Long Branch to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 4)
- March 31, 1857, Letter from Adelaide to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 5)
- April 6, 1837, Letter from Adelaide to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 6)
- April 13, 1857, Letter from Adelaide Nelson to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 7)
- April 25, 1857, Letter from Adelaide, in Long Branch, to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 8)
- April 28, 1857, Letter from Mother Adelaide, in Long Branch, Nannie (Box 1, Folder 9)
- May 4, 1857, Letter from Harriet L. Scollay, in Middleway, to Cousin Nannie (Box 1, Folder 10)
- May 9, 1857, Letter from Adelaide, to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 11)
- May 11, 1857, Letter from Hugh Nelson to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 12)
- May 16, 1857, Letter from Adelaide, to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 13)
- May 20, 1857, Letter from Mother, in Long Branch, to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 14)
- June 5, 1857, Letter from Cousin Mevllie Scollay, in Middleway, to Cousin Nannie (Box 1, Folder 15)
- June 14, 1857, Letter from Adelaide, to Nannie (Box 1, Folder 16)
- November 5, 1957, Letter to Nelson from Shier Wilie in Boston, (Re: 'The Bight' (a house), taxes $175, business transactions, discuss rent and repairs, mentions hard economic conditions) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- July 1, 1858, University of Virginia announcement (Re: Final exercises, best debater, Charles Stringfellow, sent by Bennett Taylor) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- April 9, 1860, Letter to Nelson from C. Aar, discuss 1860 elections (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Capt. Joseph Hardesty, 1st Regiment Cavalry Muster Roll, Signed: JEB Stuart (Harper's Ferry, Shephardstown enrollments, Berryville, people mustered by Stuart) (Folder 1)
- Muster Roll, Pay Roll, Capt. Hugh M. Nelson, Co. D, First Virginia Cavalry, JEB Stuart Command, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Muster Roll, Capt. Hugh M. Nelson, Co. D Sixth Cavalry, Col. Charles W. Field, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- September 21, 1861, Letter to Mrs. Hugh Nelson from Insurance agent (re: burning of the green house) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- November 1, 1861, Muster Roll Company D, 6th Regiment (Folder 1)
- November 1, 1861, Muster Roll, Company D, Sixth Regiment (Folder 1)
- November 5, 1861, Letter from Hugh Nelson, at Carter Hall, to sister (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Wrapper, envelope- war letters, no letters contained, envelope addressed to Col. A.R. Boteler, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- February 11, 1862, Orders Concerning Recruitment (Box 1, Folder 28)
- February 12, 1862, Letter to Capt. Hugh M. Nelson, Co. D, 6th Regiment, Virginia Cavalry, from Camp GW Smith, Special Order No. 40, Recruiting (Box 1, Folder 29)
- March 4, 1862, Statement of enlistment order, Capt. Hugh M. Nelson, Clarke Cavalry Co. D, 6th regiment (?), Virginia Cavalry (Box 1, Folder 30)
- April 6, 1862, Letter to Hugh M. Nelson from T. K. Fauntleroy, Gordon, commanding ordnance depot at Gordonsville, re: sabres and JEB Stuart's orders (Box 1, Folder 31)
- July 6, 1863, "Home," letter to Wash from Cousin Molly S. Award of Gettysburg and loss of 10,000 Men (Box 2, Folder 1)
- October 25, 1863, To Mollie from Wash in Westwood and March 31, 1865, To Mollie from Wash in Fort Delaware (Two Letters to One Envelope) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- October 28, 1863, Letter to Mollie from Wash in Winchester, Telling Mollie of his Capture (Box 2, Folder 3)
- December 20, 1863, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island, Ohio), from M.N.S. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- December 30, 1863, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island, Ohio), from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 5)
- January 16, 1864, Letter to Cap. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. Johnson's Island, Ohio) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- January 30, 1864, To Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island, Ohio) from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 7)
- February 9, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Johnson's Island, Ohio (Box 2, Folder 8)
- February 25, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Johnson's Island, Ohio (Box 2, Folder 9)
- February 26, 1864, To Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island, Ohio), from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 10)
- March 2, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island, Ohio) from M (Box 2, Folder 11)
- March 8, 1864, March 27, 1864,Two letters in one envelope; Both to Mollie, from Wash in Johnson's Island (Box 2, Folder 12)
- March 13, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W. at Point Lookout, MD) from sister (Box 2, Folder 13)
- March 14, 1864, Letter to Mollie from Wash in Johnson's Island (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 1864, Letter to mollie, from Capt. Wash Nelson (P.O.W. at Johnson's Island) the envelope has "Div:38 Fort Delaware, Delaware" (Box 2, Folder 15)
- April 5, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson, Hd.Qtrs, Gen. Pendleton's Corps from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 16)
- May 23, 1864 and June 14, 1864, Two letters in one envelope, to Mollie, from Wash, Point Lookout; and letter to Mollie from Wash, Hammund General Hospital, Point Lookout (Box 2, Folder 17)
- May 30, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Harrimand General Hospital, Point Lookout (Box 2, Folder 18)
- June 3, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Point Lookout, MD (Box 2, Folder 19)
- June 6, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Point Lookout, MD, from M (Box 2, Folder 20)
- June 7, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, Point Lookout (Box 2, Folder 21)
- June 12, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, Point Lookout (Box 2, Folder 22)
- June 17, 1864, Letter Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Point Lookout, MD (Box 2, Folder 23)
- June 22, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Point Lookout, MD (Box 2, Folder 24)
- June 22, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, Point Lookout (Box 2, Folder 25)
- June 26, 1864, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.), Point Lookout, MD, From M (Box 2, Folder 26)
- June 28, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Fort Delaware, (Envelope Contains a small note- [To Mollie from Dune-requests a book] and Another letter to "My Dear Friend," from Haley Curtis-no date) (Box 2, Folder 27)
- 1864, Letter to Miss Mollie N. Scollay, Shepherdstown, VA, from Wash (Box 2, Folder 28)
- October 31, 1864, Letter to Mollie, from Wash Nelson, Ft. Pulaski (Box 2, Folder 29)
- October 1865 - March 1866, Letters from C.A. Welch to Cousin (Mrs. Hugh Nelson) (Box 2, Folder 30)
- 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash Nelson, Fort Delaware (Box 2, Folder 31)
- March 21, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Ft. Delaware, DE, from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 32)
- March 24, 1865, Letter to Capt. G. W. Nelson (P.O.W.), Ft. Delaware, DE, from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 33)
- April 4, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.), Ft. Delaware, DE, from Mollie (Box 2, Folder 34)
- April 2, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 35)
- April 6, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 36)
- April 9, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Ft. Delaware, DE, (Pressed Flowers inside Envelope) (Box 2, Folder 37)
- April 12, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash Nelson in Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 38)
- April 15, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Div. 34- Ft. Delaware, DE (Box 2, Folder 39)
- April 15, 1865, Letter to Mollie from Wash in Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 40)
- April 28, 1865 and April 23, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.), from Mollie, Letter to (same); Two letters in one Envelope (Box 2, Folder 41)
- May 3, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 42)
- May 4, 1865, Letter to Mollie, From Wash, Ft. Delaware (Box 2, Folder 43)
- May 10, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash in Ft. Delaware (Box 3, Folder 1)
- May 14, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, in Ft. Delaware (Box 3, Folder 2)
- May 21, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W) Ft. Delaware, DE. from Mollie (Box 3, Folder 3)
- May 27, 1865, Letter to Wash from Mollie (Box 3, Folder 4)
- May 27, 1865, Letter to Mollie, from Wash, Ft. Delaware (Box 3, Folder 5)
- June 3, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson (P.O.W.) Division 38, Ft. Delaware, DE (Box 3, Folder 6)
- July 11, 1865 and April 9, 1866, Letters to Cousin, from Charles (C.A.W.) (C.A. Welch), Boston (Box 3, Folder 7)
- July 12, 1865, Letter to G.W. Nelson in Beaver Dam Depot, Hanover County, VA, from Mollie (Box 3, Folder 8)
- September 25, 1865, Letter to Capt. G.W. Nelson in Gettysburg, PA, from Mollie (Box 3, Folder 9)
- September 4, 1865, Letter to Mollie in Middleway, Jefferson County, VA, from Wash in Mont Air (Box 3, Folder 10)
- December 8, 1871 and February 19, 1872, Letters to Mrs. G.W. Nelson (Mollie) from her mother, S.P. Scollay (Box 3, Folder 11)
- January 29, 1872, Letter to Mollie from Mother, S.P. Scollay, in Middleway W. VA at Smithfield, Mollie has Daughter Page and siste Lizzie. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- February 18, 1783, Letter from Walker Daniel, at Col. Floyd's, to a French Merchant concerning commercial conditions on the wester Kentucky Frontier Both are friends of Col. Floyd, mentions Lincon, Fayette, Fall's of Ohio River, KY River' number of inhabitants; Indians; type of settlers; crops grown. (Merchant- Monsieur Major B. Tardiveau); No. 33 Louisville (Box 3, Folder 13)
- March 23 (year unknown), Letter from Delaide in Long Branch to "My Precious Little Child" (Box 3, Folder 14)
- March 30 (no year), Letter from Smithfield to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 15)
- March 30 and April 8, Two Envelopes to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 16)
- April 6 (no year), Envelope to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 17)
- April 10 (no year), Letter to Nannie from Adelaide in Long Beach (Box 3, Folder 18)
- April 30 (no year), Letter to Nannie from Adelaide (Box 3, Folder 19)
- No Date, Letter from Adelaid in Long Beach, to Nannie, Envelope included, 2 small pieces of paper, one is a note (Box 3, Folder 20)
- May 8 (no year), Letter from L.B. Nelson, Weehaul to Miss Nannie Nelson, Pelham Priory, Westchester, New York (Box 3, Folder 21)
- May 8 (no year), Envelope to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 22)
- May 22 (no year), Envelope to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 23)
- May 22 (no year), Envelope to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 24)
- May 25 (no year), Letter from Hugh and Mother to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 25)
- May 25 (no year), Letter from Hugh M. Nelson, New York, to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 26)
- June 5 (no year), Letter from Adelaide to Nannie (Box 3, Folder 27)
- June 6 (no year), Letter from Mother to Nannie, letter included a pressed flower and a note from Little Hugh (Box 3, Folder 28)
- August (no date), Letter to Mollie from Wash (married), Aunt Adelaide (Box 3, Folder 29)
- (No Date), Envelope (empty), "Copy of Commission Gen. Thomas Nelson by General Washington" (Box 3, Folder 30)
- (No Date), Envelope Cover, Hugh M. Nelson, Near Millwood (Box 3, Folder 31)
- (No Date), Hugh M. Nelson Accounts (Box 3, Folder 32)
- (No Date), Remnants of European Tour (Box 3, Folder 33)
- (No Date), Letter "Thursday Morning" from Adelaide, to Nannie (includes note from Hugh Nelson) (Box 3, Folder 34)
- (No Date), "Saturday, March" from mother to daughter, (March) (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Correspondence
  - Letters to/from Mollie and Wash
  - Letters to/from Adelaide
  - Envelopes and Covers Not Attached to Letters
- Papers